Putting that aside, Araragi-san.
（八九寺(はちくじ)）
それはともかく 阿良々木(あららぎ)さん
（阿良々木）何だよ
What?
I'm hungry.
私は おなかが すいていますよ？
Animation Number 005A
Then let's go eat somewhere once Senjougahara comes back.
（阿良々木）
じゃあ 戦場ヶ原(せんじょうがはら)が戻ってきたら
どっかに何か食べに行こうぜ
Do you have anything you like to eat?
お前 何か好きな食べ物とか
あるのか？
フフン
I like any kind of food.
（八九寺）
食べ物であれば 何でも好きです
（阿良々木）ふうん
Your hands were also rather tasty.
阿良々木さんの手も
おいしかったです
My hands are not food.
（阿良々木）
僕の手は食べ物じゃない
You're just being humble. They really were tasty.
またまた ご謙遜を
おいしかったのは本当です
Speaking of which, you probably really did swallow some of my flesh and blood,
（阿良々木）
ていうか お前は多分
マジで僕の血肉
少なからず
飲み込んじゃってるから
その発言は
かなりシャレにならないぞ
so I can't exactly take your words lightly.
- By the way, Hachikuji. Is it true
that you went to your mother's house?
（阿良々木）
八九寺 僕には
よく分からないけれど
- By the way, Hachikuji. Is it true
that you went to your mother's house?
It's true.
I'm not lying.
- I see ... ...
お前は
お母さんに会いたいんだよな？
- I see ... ...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
Still,
"it had been quite some time,
so she became lost"...
...I don't think that is the reason.
Since she ran into the snail,
even though this is not the place where it started...
...I don't think that is the reason.
Since she ran into the snail,
even though this is not the place where it started...
...I don't think that is the reason.
Since she ran into the snail,
even though this is not the place where it started...
...I don't think that is the reason.
Since she ran into the snail,
even though this is not the place where it started...
...I don't think that is the reason.
Since she ran into the snail,
even though this is not the place where it started...
...I don't think that is the reason.
Since she ran into the snail,
even though this is not the place where it started...
...I don't think that is the reason.
Since she ran into the snail,
even though this is not the place where it started...
...I don't think that is the reason.
Since she ran into the snail,
even though this is not the place where it started...
...I don't think that is the reason.
Since she ran into the snail,
even though this is not the place where it started...
...I don't think that is the reason.
Since she ran into the snail,
even though this is not the place where it started...
...I don't think that is the reason.
Since she ran into the snail,
even though this is not the place where it started...
...I don't think that is the reason.
Since she ran into the snail,
even though this is not the place where it started...
...I don't think that is the reason.
Since she ran into the snail,
even though this is not the place where it started...
...I don't think that is the reason.
Since she ran into the snail,
even though this is not the place where it started...
...I don't think that is the reason.
Since she ran into the snail,
even though this is not the place where it started...
No, wait...
（八九寺）
子供が
お母さんに会いたいと思うのは
No, wait...
Why did Hachikuji run into the snail?
Reason.
There was a reason why I was attacked by a vampire.
For Hanekawa's case and for Senjougahara's.
So, there should be a reason
for Hachikuji as well.
- Say, this might sound like an oversimplification, but I take it your objective
wasn't to reach the destination by itself, you just wanted to meet
your mother, right?
- "Just" is a cruel word to use, but you're correct.
- Say, this might sound like an oversimplification, but I take it your objective
wasn't to reach the destination by itself, you just wanted to meet
your mother, right?
- "Just" is a cruel word to use, but you're correct.
- Say, this might sound like an oversimplification, but I take it your objective
wasn't to reach the destination by itself, you just wanted to meet
your mother, right?
- "Just" is a cruel word to use, but you're correct.
- Say, this might sound like an oversimplification, but I take it your objective
wasn't to reach the destination by itself, you just wanted to meet
your mother, right?
- "Just" is a cruel word to use, but you're correct.
普通の感情だと思いますが
- Say, this might sound like an oversimplification, but I take it your objective
wasn't to reach the destination by itself, you just wanted to meet
your mother, right?
- "Just" is a cruel word to use, but you're correct.
- Say, this might sound like an oversimplification, but I take it your objective
wasn't to reach the destination by itself, you just wanted to meet
your mother, right?
- "Just" is a cruel word to use, but you're correct.
- Say, this might sound like an oversimplification, but I take it your objective
wasn't to reach the destination by itself, you just wanted to meet
your mother, right?
- "Just" is a cruel word to use, but you're correct.
- Say, this might sound like an oversimplification, but I take it your objective
wasn't to reach the destination by itself, you just wanted to meet
your mother, right?
- "Just" is a cruel word to use, but you're correct.
- Then why don't you ask her to come to you.
Look, even if you can't reach Tsunade-san's house, your mother is not confined there.
- It's impossible. Or more precisely, it's pointless.
That was Hachikuji's
immediate answer.
- If it were possible, I'd have done it long ago.
But it is impossible
Remaining/left-over
Ghost
違いますか？
Remaining/left-over
Ghost
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
- I can't even call my mother on the phone.
- Hmm.
- I can only visit my mother like this. Even if I knew
I can never reach her place.
Typeface used for images: HGP mincho B
Mayoi Snail, Part Three
Episode 5
Hachikuji, I don't quite understand why, but you want to see your mother, correct?
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I was under the belief that it's rather normal for children to want to see their mother. Am I wrong?
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Well, of course not, but...
（阿良々木）そりゃそうなんだけど
You live with your parents, right? That's why you don't understand.
（八九寺）
阿良々木さんは
ご両親ともに同じ家で
暮らしてらっしゃるんでしょう？
だから 分からないんです
If you lived by yourself, I think you would want to see them, too.
離れて暮らせば
阿良々木さんだって
絶対に会いたくなると思います
Is that how it is?
（阿良々木）そんなものかね
From the way you've been speaking, I get the feeling that you don't really like your parents.
（八九寺）
先ほどからの 口ぶりからすると
阿良々木さんは
あまり ご両親のことを
好いていないような印象を
受けますが
（阿良々木）
あ〜 そうじゃないよ
ただな　うん…
It's not like that. I just...
Up until middle school, I was a really good kid.
（阿良々木）
僕ってさ 中学までは
すっげ〜いい子だったんだよ
Dad
Animation Number 'none'
I didn't disobey my parents for any reason.
意味もなく 親に
反抗したりも
しなかったしな
Animation Number 'none'
Thank you, mother, father.
Koyomi.
I was really grateful to them for raising me.
育ててくれてることに
感謝してたんだ
ほほう ご立派です
How nice.
Naoetsu High School Textbook
Animation number 23
But when I got to high school, I fell behind in my studies.
The monkey gave the persimmon
seed to the crab.
The crab gave the rice ball
to the monkey.
Sprout quickly, persimmon seed,
if you don't, I'll cut you with my claws.
Naoetsu High School Textbook
Animation number 23
（阿良々木）
けど 高校で勉強についていけなく
なっちゃってさ
Naoetsu High School Textbook
Animation number 23
Then the good-kid image that I had maintained took a complete turn.
（阿良々木）
すると 今まで いい子だった分
反動が来てさ
I had this unspeakable, unpleasant kind of feeling.
言葉にならない
気まずさみたいなものがあってな
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Brother, you're
always like that!
Brother, you're always like that!
（火憐(かれん)）
兄ちゃんは そんなことだから
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Because of that, they said that's why no matter how much time passes, I'll never grow up.
（阿良々木）
そんなことだから 僕は
いつまでたっても
大人になれないんだってさ
Never growing up. Always just a child. Apparently.
いつまでも大人になれない
子供のままだそうだ
A child? Then you're just like me.
子供ですか
では 私と同じです
I think it's a bit different than you, honestly.
（阿良々木）
お前と一緒ってわけじゃない
と思うけどな
They probably mean something along the line of,
体ばっか でっかくなって
"He's grown up on the outside, but inside he hasn't changed at all."
中身が それに ついていってない
って意味だろうから
Feeler
But you know, Araragi-san, I'm considered quite mature amongst my classmates.
阿良々木さん これでも私
クラスでは
かなり発育の良いほうです
That's true. Your chest is pretty developed.
（阿良々木）
確かに
なかなか立派な胸をしていたな
（八九寺）ハッ！ 触りましたか？
You touched it?! When did you touch it?!
いつ触りました？
When we were fighting.
（阿良々木）
えっと 取っ組み合いしたとき
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
My first touch has been taken!
ファーストタッチを
奪われてしまいました！
First touch?
（阿良々木）ファーストタッチ？
Bee
To actually have a first touch before a first kiss!
ファーストキスより
ファーストタッチのほうが
先だなんて
Hachikuji Mayoi has turned into a pervert!
八九寺真宵(まよい)は いやらしい女の子に
なってしまいました！
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Ah, that's right, Hachikuji-chan. I completely forgot.
（阿良々木）
あっ そうだ 八九寺ちゃん
そういえば すっかり忘れてたね
I promised you that I'd give you some allowance, didn't I?
約束どおり お小遣いをあげよう
Please don't say that with such horrible timing!
このタイミングで
言わないでください！
がうっ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
がうっ がうっ がうっ
There, there, there.
どっ どうどう　よしよしよ〜し
Araragi-san, you don't look even the least bit apologetic.
阿良々木さん
反省の色が見えません
You should at least say something after touching a girl's delicate chest!
少女のデリケートな胸に
触っておいて
ひと言くらいあっても
いいでしょう！
Thanks?
Animation Number
ありがとう？
Thanks?
Animation Number
（八九寺）
違います！
謝罪を要求しています！
No, I'm asking you to apologize!
Speaking of which, it doesn't really matter, does it? It's not that big a deal.
（阿良々木）
ていうか 別にいいだろ
減るもんじゃないし
They say that they'll get bigger if you rub them.
逆に もまれたら 増えるともいうぞ
What?! You've been using that superstition as a shield
（八九寺）
何ですか！ 阿良々木さんは
そんな迷信を盾にとって
to constantly touch girls' breasts, haven't you?!
今まで婦女子の胸を
もみまくってきたのですか？
You're the worst.
最低ですね
Unfortunately, I've never had such an opportunity.
（阿良々木）
残念ながら
そんな機会は 一度もなかったな
I see you're just a stupid virgin, aren't you?
（八九寺）童貞野郎なんですね！
（阿良々木）あっ
How can you know, elementary school student?
Animation Number 51
（八九寺）がう！ がうう！
（阿良々木）いっ う…
（八九寺）がうがう がうがう！
（阿良々木）あっ 危ねえって！
That's dangerous! Seriously, it's dangerous!
（阿良々木）まじ ヤバいって！
I've been touched by a virgin! I've been contaminated!
（八九寺）
童貞に触られました！
汚されました！
It's the same no matter who touches you!
（阿良々木）
誰に触られたって同じだ
そんなもん！
ようやく芽生えかけていた罪悪感が
消えていくぞ！
I'm beginning to lose my slight feeling of guilt!
（八九寺）がう〜
がう がうっ がうっ がう！
Quarrel
I can't take it anymore! What are you, a rabid dog?!
ああ もう狂犬病か お前は！
こうなったらもう
Since it's like this, who cares about the first?! Who cares about a kiss?!
ファーストが どうとか
キスが何とか
I'll rub your chest until you don't care about that anymore!
そんなことが
気にならなくなる くらいに
GROPE
もみしだいて やらあ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
There was a high school boy who was going to forcibly sexually harass an elementary school girl.
（阿良々木）
小学生女子を相手に 我を忘れ
強引なセクハラ行為を
力任せに迫る男子高校生の姿が
そこにはあった… が
But... just this once, I don't want to believe that's me.
それだけは 僕ではないと信じたい
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Five minutes later
Animation number 62
I'm sorry...
（八九寺）ごめんなさいでした
Wound
No,
いや—
I should be the one apologizing.
こっちこそ ごめん
But Hachikuji, you sure know how to put up a fight.
（阿良々木）
しかし 八九寺
割とケンカ慣れしてるな お前
It happens a lot in school. You put up a good fight, too.
（八九寺）
学校では よくあることです
阿良々木さんこそ
Araragi
|
I used to always fight like that with my sister.
（阿良々木）
あんな感じの取っ組み合いなら
妹相手に しょっちゅうでね
I suppose this sort of fight is over if one side apologizes...
まあ 取っ組み合いのケンカなら
どっちかが謝って
終わりなんだよな
What's wrong, Ararararagi-san?
（八九寺）どうかされましたか？
阿良々々々木(あららららぎ)さん
This time there are two extra "ra"s.
（阿良々木）
今度は“ら”が２個多いからな
Pardon me. I stuttered.
失礼 かみました
Ararararagi
|
Arararagi
Araragi
|
No, that was on purpose.
（阿良々木）違う わざとだ
I st-stuttered.
かみまみた
It wasn't on purpose!?
（阿良々木）わざとじゃない！
I can't help it. Everyone misspeaks at some point.
（八九寺）しかたがありません
誰だって言い間違いを
することくらいは あります
Or are you saying that you haven't stuttered once since you were born?
それとも 阿良々木さんは
生まれてから 一度も
かんだことがない
というのですか？
Not exactly, but at least I don't stutter when saying someone else's name.
ないとは言わないが
少なくとも
人の名前をかんだりはしないよ
では
Then, please say "nanamumi nanamome namamamamo" three times.
Namamumi
Namamome
Namamamamo
Animation Number 78
生(なま)むみ 生(なま)もめ 生(なま)ままも
と３回言ってください
You didn't even say it right.
お前が言えてないじゃん
Animation Number 79B
Namamome
Namamome is so obscene!
（八九寺）
生もめだなんて
いやらしいです！
Bashful
（阿良々木）
言ったのは
お前だからな
You said it, not me.
Animation Number 80B
Namamamamo
Namamamamo is obscene, too!
（八九寺）
生ままもだなんて
いやらしいです！
Bashful
How is that obscene? I don't really get it...
（阿良々木）
そのいやらしさは
僕には分からないが
Speaking of which, won't saying it intentionally be more difficult?
（阿良々木）ていうか
意図的に言おうと思えば
かえって
言いにくい言葉だろう
Namamamamo.
Namamamamo
生ままも
Namamamamo!
（八九寺）
生ままま〜
Namamamamo
Mitsuo (uso)
Stuttering and
stuttering makes for
a hurried man.
Then may I know what happened, Araragi-san?
（八九寺）
で どうかされましたか
阿良々木さん
Nothing much.
（阿良々木）どうもしないよ
I just thought of how I should apologize to my sister, and I got a bit depressed.
ただ 妹に どんなふうに
謝ったもんかを考えると
ちょっと
憂鬱になっちまっただけだ
Having to apologize...
謝るということは
胸でも もみましたか？
Don't tell me you touched her breasts?
Who would touch their own sister's breasts?
妹の胸なんか もむか
When I left the house today, I sort of had a quarrel with my sister.
（阿良々木）
今日 家を出るとき
妹とちょっと口論しちまってな
I used to fight constantly with my mother and father, too.
（八九寺）
私のお父さんとお母さんも
ケンカばかりしてました
Not physically, though.
取っ組み合いじゃないですよ
口論のほうです
Only verbally.
（阿良々木）ん…
As an only daughter, it's not really my place to say this, but...
一人娘の私が言うのも何ですが
仲のいいご夫婦だった
らしいのですよ
They looked like a happy couple on the surface.
But I've never seen them get along...
ですが 私は
仲良くしている お２人というのを
見たことが なかったんです
They were constantly fighting.
お二人は いつも
ケンカばかりしてました
You love your mother, don't you?
（阿良々木）
お前は
お母さんのことが好きなんだよな
Yes, I love her.
（八九寺）ええ 好きです
Of course, I love my father as well.
もちろん
お父さんのことも好きです
（阿良々木）うん
Even though my father and mother fought constantly and eventually split up, I still love them both.
（八九寺）
お父さんとお母さんはケンカをされ
その結果
別れてしまいましたけれど
私は お２人とものことを
大好きなんです
I see.
（阿良々木）そっか
That's why, because of that, I'm feeling uneasy.
（八九寺）
だから だからこそ不安です
My father seems to hate my mother a lot.
お父さん お母さんのこと
本気で嫌いになっちゃったみたいで
Because of that, he doesn't let me see her.
私を お母さんに
会わそうとしないんです
I wonder, if this continues, will I forget my mother someday?
私 お母さんのこと
いつか忘れちゃうんじゃないかって
If I can never see her again, will I stop loving her someday?
このまま ずっと会えなければ
お母さんのこと
好きじゃなくなっちゃうんじゃ
ないかって
I'm so uneasy...
とても不安です
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I smell another woman.
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（戦場ヶ原）
ほかの女の匂いが
するわね
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
O-Oh, Senjougahara.
お… おお 戦場ヶ原
This scent of shampoo...
このシャンプーの香りは
It belongs to Hanekawa-san, doesn't it?
羽川(はねかわ)さんかしらね
え？ お前 分かるの？
You can tell?
To a certain extent.
ある程度はね
You can also think of it as using the shape of the waist to differentiate women.
阿良々木くんが 腰の形で
女子を区別できるのと
同じようなものと
考えてくれていいわ
I don't remember displaying such special abilities.
（阿良々木）
そんな特殊な能力を
披露した覚えはねえよ
（戦場ヶ原）
え？ あれ？ できないの？
You can't do it?
Don't react like it's not ordinary!
（阿良々木）
意外そうなリアクションをするな！
You have an outstanding pelvic stance. It looks rather suitable for childbirth,
（戦場ヶ原）
“お前は据わりのいい
立派な骨盤をした安産型だから”
so I think you'll be able to give birth to a healthy baby.
“きっと 元気な赤ちゃんが
産めると思うぜ”
“ウエッヘッヘッヘッヘッ”て
Didn't you say that to me recently?
この間 私に言ってくれたじゃない
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（阿良々木）
あ？ ただの変態野郎じゃねえか！
Those were the words of some other pervert out there!
Then, Hanekawa-san came, didn't she?
（戦場ヶ原）
で 羽川さん 来てたのね
（阿良々木）
まあ 来てたよ
もう帰ったけれど
Yeah, she came.
She already went home, though.
She merely passed by.
たまたま通りかかったんだ
（戦場ヶ原）ふうん
You must have heard the details from Oshino-san, right, Senjougahara?
で 忍野(おしの)から話 聞いてきたんだろ？
戦場ヶ原
Araragi-kun, it seems that I have to apologize to you.
阿良々木くん 私はどうやら
謝らなければいけないそうよ
Oshino-san told me I should.
忍野さんに
そう言われてしまったわ
What could you possibly need to apologize for?
（阿良々木）
は？ 謝らなければならないこと？
Even if there's only one actual truth, you can have two truths from two different perspectives.
（戦場ヶ原）
正しい事実が１つあったとして
それを２つの視点から観察したとき
違う結果が出たとする
A method to determine which truth is true doesn't actually exist.
そのとき どちらの視点が
正しいかを判断する方法は
本来 ない
There's no real method of proving your truth in this world.
自分の正しさを証明する方法なんて
この世にはないのだと
But believing that you're wrong for that reason is also wrong.
（戦場ヶ原）
でも だからって 自分が
間違っていると決めつけるのも
同じくらい違う
He talks as if he can see right through you.
だって　ホント あの人は
見透かしたことを言うわよね
I hate that.
嫌いだわ
（阿良々木）
いや 何 言ってんだ？ お前
What the hell are you saying?
No, not you, but rather Oshino.
いや お前じゃなくて忍野か？
What you said doesn't seem to have any connection with the current situation.
この状況に そんなの
あまり関係がありそうにも
思えないけれど
The way to get released from the snail, the lost cow, is apparently rather simple.
（戦場ヶ原）蝸牛(かたつむり)—
迷(まよ)い牛(うし)から解放される方法は
とても簡単なのだそうよ
阿良々木くん
You get lost because you follow the snail, so if you go away from it, you won't be lost.
“蝸牛に
ついていくから迷うのであって”
“蝸牛から離れれば迷いはない”
だって
You get lost because you follow it?
ついていくから迷う？
In the case of the snail, it seems that the human that becomes its target is led astray.
蝸牛の場合
対象となっている人間のほうから
怪異(かいい)のほうに寄っているらしいの
That's why you only need to get away from the snail.
だから 阿良々木くんが
蝸牛から離れれば
それでいいというわけ
No, not me, right? Hachikuji does.
（阿良々木）
いや 僕じゃないだろ 八九寺がだよ
But if it's like that, don't you find it weird?
でも それなら おかしいじゃないか
She didn't follow the snail on her own.
八九寺は別に 自分から蝸牛に
ついていっているわけじゃ
There's no way she'd want that.
そんなこと
望んでるわけないじゃないか
That's why I need to apologize to you, Araragi-kun.
だから
私は あなたに謝らなくては
ならないのよ 阿良々木くん
But, even so, I hope you'll let me explain.
（戦場ヶ原）
でも それでも
言い訳は させてちょうだい
I didn't have any bad intentions.
悪気が
あったわけではなかったし
Besides, it wasn't on purpose.
それに わざとでもなかったの
I thought for certain that I had made a mistake.
私は てっきり
私が間違っているんだ
と思っていたのよ
Senjougahara...
戦場ヶ原？
Well, think about it.
（戦場ヶ原）
だって そうでしょう？
For over two years, I have not been normal.
２年以上もの間
私は普通じゃなかったんだもの
If something happened, I would think that it was my fault.
何かあったら 私のほうが
間違ってると思ってしまうのも
It can't be helped.
しかたがなかったのよ
Hey, Senjougahara...
（阿良々木）おい… 戦場ヶ原
Hachikuji-chan, is it?
八九寺ちゃん よね
（阿良々木）あ…
Basically, Araragi-kun...
（戦場ヶ原）
つまりね 阿良々木くん
You felt bad on Mother's Day, fought with your sister, didn't want to go back home...
母の日で気まずくて
妹さんとケンカして
家に帰りたくない 阿良々木くん
That girl...
その子
I can't see her.
私には見えないのよ
（阿良々木）あっ
It was just about 10 years ago.
（八九寺）
ほんの10年ほど前の話です
At a certain place, a husband and wife walked toward the end of marriage.
あるところで１組の夫婦が
その関係に終えんを迎えました
It was decided that their only daughter would go with the father.
夫婦の 一人娘は
父親が引き取ることになりました
No matter what one's memories are, they get worn down.
どんな思いも風化していきます
どんな思いも劣化していきます
No matter what one's memories are, they deteriorate.
With the flow of time, the only daughter was shocked.
時が過ぎ 一人娘は驚きました
She no longer remembered her mother's face.
自分の母親の顔が
思い出せなくなっていたのです
For you
About you
With you
Even if she looked at her mother's photos,
母親の写真を見ても
she couldn't tell if that was really her own mother anymore.
それが本当に
自分の母親なのかどうか
Bakemonogatari
Story two
分からなくなっていました
Because she is the mother
That's why the only daughter decided to go see her mother on the Mother's Day of that year.
だから 一人娘は
母親に会いにいくことにしました
Because she is the mother
Maybe you
were hated?
Don't you think
you were forgotten?
Weren't you
a bother for here?
Because she is the mother
After all, I'm her only daughter
After all, I'm her
その年の母の日に
After all, I'm her only daughter
After all, I'm her
For you
About you
With you
After all, I'm her only daughter
After all, I'm her
Still Still Still Still Still Still Still
But she did not reach her mother's home.
けれど
一人娘は たどり着けませんでした
Still Still Still Still Still Still Still
even so even so even so
even so even so even so even so
母親の家には
たどり着けませんでした
mother I mother I mother I mother I mother I mother I mother I
I wonder why. Why?
どうしてでしょう
love you so much love you so much love you so much love
love you so much love you so much love you so much love you so much love you so much
どうしてでしょう
本当に どうしてなんでしょう？
Really, why was that?
if possible, you too if possible, you too if possible, you too if possible, you too if possible, you too if possible, you too
The traffic light was clearly green.
信号は確かに青色だったのに
please love me back please love me back please love me back please love me back please love me back please love me back
That only daughter is me.
その 一人娘というのが私です
（阿良々木）あっ
From then on, were you always lost?
以来 ずっと迷ってる
っていうのか お前は
A person who cannot reach her destination will hinder another person's way home.
（戦場ヶ原）
目的地に たどり着けなかった者が
他者の帰り道を阻害する
巡り巡る巡礼
Going around in circles.
Basically, Hachikuji.
つまり八九寺だそうよ
でも
But are you sure you can't see Hachikuji?
（八九寺）ん…
（阿良々木）本当に お前
（阿良々木）
八九寺が見えてねえっていうのか？
No, I can't even hear her voice.
（戦場ヶ原）
見えないわ 声も聞こえない
But you were acting so naturally...
（阿良々木）だって お前 普通に
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I can't see that sort of thing.
見えないわよ そんなの
（阿良々木）あっ
The only thing I see is a person talking to himself.
私に見えていたのは
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
ぶつぶつ独り言を言って
The last thing I saw was Araragi-kun going crazy.
最後には１人で暴れだした
阿良々木くんだけ
I totally didn't understand what you were doing.
何をしているのか
全く分からなかったわ
（阿良々木）あ…
でも
それならそうと言ってくれれば
If it's like that, you only need to tell me...
Like I said, there's no way I could just say it.
だから 言えるわけないじゃない
It's impossible for me to just say it.
言えるわけがないわ
If such a thing happened... If the thing that you could see, I couldn't...
そんなことがあれば
阿良々木くんに見えるものが
私に見えなければ
Then I would normally think that it's me that has a problem.
見えない私のほうが
おかしいんだって
私は普通に思うわよ
（阿良々木）
そうか
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
That's right.
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Senjougahara doesn't want to feel that something is wrong with her again.
戦場ヶ原は またおかしくなった
だなんて思いたくなくて
She doesn't want to feel that she became abnormal once again...
おかしくなってしまっただなんて
思いたくなくて
She doesn't want me to feel that way either...
僕に そんなことを
思われたくなくて
見えていない八九寺のことを
見えているふりをした
That's why she pretended to be able to see Hachikuji.
So that's how it is.
Animation Number 181
I see.
そうか
The one who ran into the snail... was me?
Animation Number 182
蝸牛に行き遭ったのは
僕だったのか
Araragi-kun, Oshino-san said that the criteria for meeting the lost cow is the desire not to return home.
（戦場ヶ原）
阿良々木くん
忍野さんが こう言っていたわ
迷い牛に会うための条件
っていうのは
家に帰りたくないと
望んでいることなんだって
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（阿良々木）あっ！
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
But everyone thinks that sometimes.
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（戦場ヶ原）
でも そのくらい
誰でも考えることよね
Every family has their problems, no matter who they are.
家庭の事情なんて誰にでもあるもの
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
She's the same.
（阿良々木）
あいつもまた そうだった
Friction and strain in her family...
家庭に不和とゆがみを抱えていて
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
But because of that, Araragi-kun, dealing with the lost cow is very simple.
（戦場ヶ原）
けれどね だからこそ阿良々木くん
迷い牛への対処は
とても簡単なのよ
I said from the start that as long as you stop following it and distance yourself, it'll be okay.
最初に言ったでしょう？
ついていかずに離れればいいのよ
That's all you need to do...
それだけのことなの
"It's a strange thing that isn't very evil or strong."
そんな悪質な怪異じゃないし
そこまで強力な怪異でもない
"It isn't really a dangerous threat in the first place." That's what he said.
まず大きな害はない
そう言ってたわ
Animation Number 188
So.
That's why...
だから
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
That's why...?
Animation Number 188
So?
（阿良々木）
だから？
Then what, Senjougahara?
だから何だよ 戦場ヶ原
What I mean is how to get this girl-
僕が聞きたかったのは
こいつを 八九寺を
Animation Number 193B
Separation
How to get Hachikuji to her mother's place.
お母さんのところに
一体どうやったら
Animation Number 193C
Divorce
Animation Number 193D
Bereavement
連れていってやれるか
ってことだ
Animation Number 194
Do you understand, Araragi-kun?
（戦場ヶ原）
分かってるの？ 阿良々木くん
This child does not exist there.
その子 そこには いないのよ
She does not exist there, nor does she exist anywhere.
そこには いないし
どこにも いないのよ
Hachikuji. The child called Hachikuji Mayoi-chan...
八九寺 八九寺真宵ちゃん
っていうんだっけ その子は
is already dead.
もう死んでるの
That's why this child is not being possessed by something, but is that something itself.
だから その子は
怪異に取りつかれてるんじゃなくて
怪異そのもので
ハッ それがどうした
So what?
A-Araragi-san, it hurts.
あ… 阿良々木さん 痛いです
Araragi-san, everything is exactly as Senjougahara-san said.
（八九寺）あ… あの 阿良々木さん
この方の
戦場ヶ原さんの言うとおりです
私—
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
I... I'm...
Red Scene
Animation Number 'none'
私は
Shut up!
（阿良々木）黙ってろ！
You may not have heard it, Senjougahara.
お前には聞こえなかったんだよな
戦場ヶ原
This girl said some really outrageous things to me and Hanekawa from the start.
こいつは僕に対しても
羽川に対しても
ひと言目から
いきなりとんでもないことを
ぬかしやがったんだ
Please don't speak to me. I hate you.
（八九寺）
話しかけないでください
Mayoi Hachikuji
Class 5-3
Animation number 203B
あなたのことが嫌いです
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Do you understand, Senjougahara?
（阿良々木）分かるか？ 戦場ヶ原
Because she doesn't want anyone to follow her, that's why she says such things to everyone she meets.
ついてきてほしくないからって
会う人間全員に
そんなセリフを言わなくちゃ
いけないヤツの気持ちが
Can you understand that?!
お前に分かるってのか？
I totally don't understand, but even so, when I was missing and when I was all alone,
僕には全く分からないぞ
でも 分からなくても それでも
自分が道に迷っているときに
the feeling of having the need to say such things...
１人でいるときに そういうことを
言わなくちゃならない気持ちを
それでも 僕もお前も
You and I... haven't we experienced the same thing, just in a different way?!
違う形で
経験してきているはずだろう
Even though you can't see her, hear her voice, or even smell her...
お前には見えないし聞こえないし
匂いすらも
感じないんだろうけれど
Even so... That's why...
それでも それだからこそ
It's my duty to bring her safely to her mother's side.
こいつを無事に母親の所にまで
送り届けるのが
僕の役目だ
I knew you would say that.
そう言うと思ったわ
I finally understand you, Araragi-kun.
ようやく実感できたわ
阿良々木くんのこと
When you found out about my problem,
ねえ 阿良々木くん
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
阿良々木くんに
私の抱えていた問題が
バレちゃったとき
you took the initiative to speak to me on that day.
阿良々木くんは その日のうちに
私に声をかけてくれたわよね
Why is that so?
どうしてかしら
Did you perhaps offer help solely because it was me?
阿良々木くんは ひょっとして
私だから助けてくれたのかしら？
（阿良々木）ん…
But that wasn't the case.
（戦場ヶ原）
でも そうじゃなかった
そうじゃなかったみたい
That wasn't the case.
It was purely...
そうじゃなくて単純に
Say, Araragi...
Animation number 221D
because you'll save anyone, right?
Say, Araragi...
Animation number 221D
阿良々木くんって
誰でも助けるだけなのね
Say, Araragi...
Animation number 221D
Save them... it's nothing that amazing. You're exaggerating.
（阿良々木）
助けるって
そんな大それたことじゃないだろ
大げさに言うなよ
But two years after encountering that strange thing, even though many people realized my problem...
でも
怪異に行き合ってから２年以上
私の抱えている問題に気付いた人は
たくさんいたけれど
the only person like you was you.
阿良々木くんみたいなのは
阿良々木くんだけだったから
Well, sure. I'm just me.
そりゃ まあ 僕は僕だけだろうよ
That's right. Of course.
そうね そのとおりだわ
Mayoi Hachikuji
Animation number 221D
This is the last message Oshino-san left, Araragi-kun.
忍野さんからの最後の伝言よ
阿良々木くん
"Just this once, I'll teach you a trick that can be of use."
今回に限り使えるだろう裏技を
１つ伝授しておこうって
（阿良々木）う… 裏技？
Trick?
Okay, let's go.
（戦場ヶ原）じゃあ 行くわよ
（阿良々木）行くって どこへ
Go? Where to?
To Tsunade-san's house, of course.
（戦場ヶ原）
もちろん 綱手さんのおうちよ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
And, Araragi-kun...
それから 阿良々木くん
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
何だよ
What?
（戦場ヶ原）
アイ ラブ ユー
Congratulations.
おめでとうございます
The lost cow, as an anomaly, is a ghost-type.
（阿良々木）
迷い牛の怪異としての属性が
幽霊であるのなら
A
Under construction
Halted
Due to this, it can't store new
information-oriented memories.
そこには情報的記憶が蓄積しない
Information-oriented memories are, basically, knowledge.
情報的記憶とは つまり知識だ
We're here.
（戦場ヶ原）着いたわ
Huh?
Animation Number 243
It's understandable for a person like me who has no geographic knowledge at all.
（阿良々木）
僕のような土地勘のない者は
もちろん
蝸牛が見えてすらいない
戦場ヶ原でさえ
But for Senjougahara, who can't even see the snail, to be lost...
迷わせることができる
Gas
Still, something you don't know will still be unknown.
が… 知らないことは知らないのだ
No. Even if you know, you will be unable to react.
いや 知っていても対応はできない
But this is...
でも こんな…
A
Rezoning Laws
Chapter one - General rules
(Article 1 - Article 3.4)
Chapter two - Contractors
Section one - Individual contractors
(Article 4 - Article 13)
Section two - Land rezoning board
Clause one - Establishment
(Article 14 - Article 24)
Clause two - Management
(Article 25 - Article 44)
Clause three - Dissolution and joining
(Article 45 - Article 51)
Section three - Rezoning companies
(Article 51.2 - Article 51.3)
Section four - Administrative divisions and cities
(Article 52 - Article 65)
Section five - Ministry of Land, Infrastructure and Transport (MLIT)
(Article 66 - Article 71)
Section six - Urban Renaissance Agency
(Article 71.2 - Article 71.6)
Chapter three - Land rezoning projects
Clause one - General rules
(Article 72 - Article 85.4)
Clause two - Land replotting schedule
(Article 86 - Article 97)
Clause three - Provisional replotting
(Article 98 - Article 102)
Clause four - Notice of replotting
(Article 103 - Article 108)
Clause five - Price reduction compensation grants
(Article 109)
Clause six - Settlement.
(Article 110 - Article 112)
Clause seven - Laws in Relation to Rights
(Article 113 - Article 117)
Clause eight - Residence construction for allocated residential areas
(Article 117.2)
Clause nine - MLIT skilled laborer examination
(Article 117.3 - Article 117.19)
Chapter four - Charging and expenses
(Article 118 - Article 121)
Chapter five - Supervision.
(Article 122 - Article 127.2)
Chapter six - Miscellaneous rules
(Article 128 - Article 136.4)
Chapter seven - Penal regulations.
(Article 137 - Article 139)
For instance, take the district map.
（阿良々木）
例えば 区画整理
If you only choose the newly-built routes, the lost cow will be unable to react.
新しく造られた道ばかりを
選択したルートを使えば
迷い牛では対応できない
After an hour going somewhere that shouldn't even take ten minutes,
徒歩で10分かからないであろう
距離を１時間以上もかけて
we finally reached the destination.
僕らは
目的地にたどり着いた　でも…
But...
PRIVATE
private land - entry prohibited
PRIVATE LAND
Development and Construction Union
It was just an empty area.
Animation number 263
Senjougahara, are you sure this is the place?
（阿良々木）
戦場ヶ原 ここで間違いないのか？
Yes, I'm sure of it.
（戦場ヶ原）ええ 間違いないわ
I don't believe it...
こんなことって あるのかよ
Sob.
Animation Number 266
I'm home!
ただいま 帰りました！
（阿良々木）あ…
You've done well, Araragi-kun.
（戦場ヶ原）
お疲れさまでした 阿良々木くん
You were perhaps a tiny bit cool.
そこそこ格好よかったわよ
This time it's all thanks to you, though.
（阿良々木）
むしろ今回働いたのは お前だろ
Even so, that's not what I mean, you know.
（戦場ヶ原）
確かに そうかもしれないけれど
そういうことではなく… ね
By the way, Araragi-kun.
ところで 阿良々木くん
You have not given me an answer yet.
まだ返事を聞いていないのだけれど
（阿良々木）ああ
What will you do?
どうするの
No, I think you might have misunderstood something.
（阿良々木）
いや お前 ちょっと
勘違いしていると思うんだよ
Look, didn't you mention something about repaying me?
ほら お返しがどうとかも
言ってたじゃん
That was only an excuse.
（戦場ヶ原）あれは口実よ
I merely wanted you to confess on your own.
阿良々木くんのほうから
告白させようと思ってね
（阿良々木）ん？ あ…
But don't worry.
（戦場ヶ原）
でも 安心して
私は本当のところ
I don't really feel that I owe you something big.
阿良々木くんに そこまで
恩を感じているわけではないのよ
（阿良々木）え？
Because you love to help others.
だって 阿良々木くん
誰でも助けるんだもの
But even if the person that was being helped was not me...
でも 助けられたのが
私じゃなくても
Even if, from the side, I watched you help Hanekawa-san or the others...
例えば 羽川さんを助けている
阿良々木くんを
横から見ていただけでも
I would still have developed special feelings for you.
私は阿良々木くんのこと
特別に感じていたと思うわよ
Well, though I seem to have said this before...
まあ ちょっと大げさな物言いに
なってしまったけれど
If you insist, I find talking to you to be fun. That's all.
阿良々木くん
強いて言うなら 私は ただ
阿良々木くんと話すのが楽しいだけ
But we haven't really talked that much, have we?
でも まだそんなに話してないだろ
I suppose.
そうね
That's why I hope to speak more with you.
だから もっと あなたと話したい
How do I put it...?
何ていうか
ええ 阿良々木くんを
Maybe it's because I've taken a liking to you. That's why I want to try hard, or something like that anyway.
好きになる努力をしたい
って感じなのかもしれないわね
I see...
（阿良々木）そっか
All right, well how about you think of it like this?
（戦場ヶ原）
そう もういっそ
こう思ってくれてもいいのよ
Unfortunately, a psychotic virgin,
愛情に飢えている
ちょっと優しくされたら
starved for love and likely to fall for anyone who would be a little nice to her, has set her eyes on you.
誰にでも なびいちゃう
ほれっぽいメンヘル処女に
不幸にも
目をつけられてしまった… と
I see.
（阿良々木）なるほど
You are really unlucky.
（戦場ヶ原）
ついてなかったわね
普段の行いを呪いなさい
Blame it on your habitual actions.
If you are to say something stupid like, "Give me a bit of time to consider,"
（戦場ヶ原）
ここで少し考えさせてほしいなんて
ふぬけた言葉を口にしたら
I will despise you, Araragi-kun.
軽蔑するわよ 阿良々木くん
Don't let a girl feel shameful.
あまり 女に
恥をかかせるものではないわ
I get it.
（阿良々木）分かってるよ
At this point in time, I feel that I'm really horrible.
現時点で
かなり みっともないと思ってるさ
But is it all right if I offer one condition?
でも 戦場ヶ原
１つだけ 僕のほうから
条件を出してもいいか？
Not really a condition... It's more like a promise.
条件っていうか まあ
約束みたいなもんなんだけど
A promise? What is it?
約束？ 何かしら
Senjougahara, pretending to see things that you actually can't...
戦場ヶ原 見えていないものを
見えているふりしたり
Or pretending not to be able to see something you really can...
見えているものを
見えていないふりしたり
No more of that, from now on.
そういうのは今後 一切なしだ
If our views clash, then let us properly talk about it.
もしも 意見が食い違ったら
そのときは ちゃんと話し合おう
Promise me.
約束だ
A simple request.
お安い御用よ
Then let's get going. It's already getting dark.
（阿良々木）じゃ 行こうか
すっかり暗くなっちまったし
Araragi-kun, could you clearly say it for me?
阿良々木くん 一応
言葉にしておいてくれるかしら
Say it?
（阿良々木）言葉に？
Because I hate unclear relationships.
なあなあの関係は嫌だから
You mean that?
（阿良々木）ああ そういうこと
I hope this will be popular.
はやると いいよな
Huh?
はい？
"Senjougahara fascination."
戦場ヶ原 蕩(と)れ
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
Namishiro park
Koyomi, it's morning!
（火憐）
兄ちゃん！
朝だぞ こら！
You have to wake up!
（月火）
いいかげんに起きないと
ダメだよ
That's Deneb, Altair, Vega
（阿良々木）う〜ん
I promised that on Mother's Day next year, I will definitely not take a single step from home.
（阿良々木）
来年の母の日は
the summer triangle that you pointed out.
家の敷地内から絶対に
出ないという約束を
So remember
交わしたのが
よかったのかもしれない
You should definitely be at home on Mother's Day next year. From: your sisters.
I absolutely won't go out.
I will stay home no matter what.
Koyomi.
It may be a good thing.
to look at the sky.
Mom said we'll be washing the bedsheets today!
（火憐）
お母さん
今日はシーツを
洗濯するって
I finally found you, Altair,
She said that she can only start washing when you wake up!
（月火）
お兄ちゃんが起きれば
洗濯 始められるのに
って言ってるよ
though where are you, Vega?
When morning came, my sisters seemed to have calmed down.
（阿良々木）
朝には妹たちの怒りは
This is loneliness.
無事に解けたようだった
（阿良々木）
うおっ 痛い！ 痛い！
I looked up from the pitch-dark world.
Bi
Wheel
Animation Number 335B
The stars fell in the night sky, and
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
（阿良々木）あっ！
（ブレーキの音）
Black Scene
Animation Number 'none'
just when was it from?
Aren't you...?
（阿良々木）
あれ お前…
Aragi-san.
Aragi-san
Animation Number 343B
That I, who ran after you,
（八九寺）
阿良木(あらぎ)さん
You left out a "ra" this time.
（阿良々木）
それだと〝ら〞が
少ないからな
Excuse me. I stuttered.
（八九寺）
失礼 かみました
was there.
What are you doing?
（阿良々木）何してんの
あ… いえ
何といいますか
Well, how do I put it...?
Please heed my wish.
Um... I have been promoted from an earthbound spirit into a wandering spirit.
え〜っとですね
Don't be surprised.
私 無事に地縛霊から
浮遊霊へと出世しました
Listen
Which means I was promoted two ranks.
２階級特進
というわけです
to these feelings
（阿良々木）へえ
Umm, Araragi-san...
（八九寺）
あの 阿良々木さん
I will probably be around here for the time being.
私 しばらくは この辺り
of mine.
うろうろしていると
思いますから
テヘッ
Bakemonogatari
Snail
Mayoi Snail, Part Three
Bakemonogatari
Snail
Mayoi Snail, Part Three
Bakemonogatari
Snail
Mayoi Snail, Part Three
Bakemonogatari
Snail
Mayoi Snail, Part Three
Bakemonogatari
Snail
Mayoi Snail, Part Three
CONTINUED NEXT TIME
If you see me, please talk to me.
（八九寺）
見かけたら
話しかけてくださいね
CONTINUED NEXT TIME
It was just an empty area.
Animation number 263
（火憐）火憐だぜ
（月火）月火だよ
It was just an empty area.
Animation number 263
I'm Karen.
I'm Tsukihi.
（火憐）タコってさ 墨吐くじゃん
（月火）吐くね
An octopus spits ink.
Spits, huh?
There's also a fish that spits ink.
（火憐）イカもさ 墨吐くよな
（月火）吐く吐く
Spit-Spit!
You might think that's all.
（火憐）
それだけだと思ってねえ？
Eh? Don't tell me they inhale ink!
（月火）
え？ まさか墨を吸うの？
Ehh.. it's not like that.
（火憐）
いや そっちじゃなくて
（月火）
じゃあ どっち？
Well, which is it?
You know... there is a fish which spits ink!
（火憐）
なんとな 墨を吐く魚もいるんだよ
（月火）
ああ アカナマダでしょ？
Oh, it's Akanagana, right?
How do you know that?!
（火憐）
なんで知ってんの？
I know of most black things!
（月火）
黒いもののことは大体知ってるよ
Time for today's baseball quiz!
（火憐）
では ここで予告編クイズ！
（月火）
クーイズ！
Quiz!
You are a baseball pitcher.
（火憐）
あなたは野球のピッチャーです
（月火）
ピッチャー 振りかぶって投げた！
The pitcher raises his hands above his head and pitches.
But the first, second, and even the third and fourth pitch are all fouled off straight pitches!
（火憐）
しかし １球目ボール
２球目もボール
３球目 ４球目もボール
ストレートのフォアボールを
出してしまいました
（月火）
ノーコンだあ！
No control!
（火憐）
さて ここで問題です！
Now for the question!
Your fourth pitch was...
あなたが投げた４球目の球種は？
（月火）
え？
そんなの分かるわけないじゃん！
Who would know that?
（火憐）
フッフーン
It couldn't be a straight...
（月火）
まさかストレートじゃあるまいし
（２人）
次回「するがモンキー
其ノ壹(そのいち)」
Next time, Suruga Monkey Part 1.
Next Time
Suruga Monkey, Part One
It was a question of straight pitch victory or defeat!
（火憐）
直球勝負な問題だったな
It wasn't clever.
（月火）
うまくない